Guide to the Squatters' Collective Oral Histories Project OH.068
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Series II: Interviews by Amy Starecheski, 2009-2012; 564839; 23.77 Gigabytes in 154 files.; 2 sound discs (cd)
  - Dan Yafet: Oral History Interview by Amy Starecheski, 2012-07-29; 564869; 478.15 Megabytes in 5 files. (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_OH_68_ER_5)
    Dan Yafet was born in Pittsburgh in 1956, the son of a Turkish father and an American mother. He grew up in Maplewood, New Jersey and went to college at Rutgers University. Upon finishing his undergraduate education Yafet spent time in the Peace Corps teaching chemistry in Cameroon. When he returned to the United States Yafet got second Bachelor's degree from City College, and began working at the Environmental Protection Agency, but did not stay at the position for long. In 1987 he went to several meetings of an organization called the New York Nicaraguan Construction, which sent construction crews to Nicaragua. At these meetings he met people from 209 East 7th Street and ended up staying in that building after he returned from working in Nicaragua. In 1988 he got his own apartment in that building. After suffering through fires and conflicts within the building Yafet decided to leave the squatting scene. He later returned to East 7th Street in 1995.
  - David Boyle: Oral History Interview by Amy Starecheski, 2012-08-17; 564868; 1.86 Gigabytes in 5 files. (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_OH_68_ER_6)
    In his interview David Boyle talks about taking over and working on buildings on 13th street, specifically 539 and 544. He played a major role in the organizing and structure of the buildings and the East 13th Street Homesteading Coalition. His interview focuses on adverse possession and he speaks at some length about the process and decision-making regarding legalization. He also talks about the 13th street eviction and the trouble between 544 East 13th and the rest of the buildings on 13th Street.
    David Boyle was born in Richmond Hill, New York. His family moved to New Jersey when he was young, but Boyle later returned to New York to go to the New School. Before he got involved into the homesteading movement he was part the anti-nuclear movement and was a member of the Yippies.
  - Edgar Rivera: Oral History Interview by Amy Starecheski, 2012-05-20; 564867; 254.3 Megabytes in 4 files. (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_OH_68_ER_7)
    In his interview Edgar Rivera discusses gaining access to a space in Umbrella House, which he contributes to the fact that he was young, strong, and willing to work. He briefly touches on his experience as a minority in Umbrella House and the squatting community in general. He explains the different dynamics between non-native and native English speakers and the dynamics between different Latino groups. He also talks about his disapproval of the deal with UHAB, mostly because he felt there was a lack of transparency.
    Edgar Rivera was born in Colombia and moved to New York to study music at City University of New York. He was introduced to squatting and moved into Umbrella House in 1988 at the age of 22.
  - Eric Rassi: Oral History Interview by Amy Starecheski, 2012-06-02; 564866; 483.26 Megabytes in 5 files. (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_OH_68_ER_8)
    During his interview Eric Rassi recalls New York in the early 1980s and the onset of the housing crisis. He recounts series of arson and building demolitions and the Tompkins Square Park Riots in 1988. He also goes into detail about his ideology about property as a commodity and land rights. Rassi expresses his unhappiness with how the UHAB legalization process worked and the issues of financing and debt. He also briefly touches on conflicts within the building on 10th Street where he lived.
    Eric Rassi grew up in Cleveland, Ohio. In the 1970s he traveled around the country, and eventually moved to New York City in 1980. Rassi moved into a squat in 1988 after living in various places and experiencing the increasing rate of rent in the city. Rassi moved between squatted spaces, often being forced to move by fires and building evictions, and eventually settled at 10th Street, where he lived at the time of the interview.
  - Erin Williams: Oral History Interview by Amy Starecheski, 2012-04-01; 564865; 559.12 Megabytes in 5 files. (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_OH_68_ER_9)
    Erin Williams describes the ending of the squatting scene and the acceleration of gentrification until a tipping point around 2007. She moved into C-Squat around 1999 and describes her first impressions of Alphabet City as surprisingly green but still just starting to gentrify. She talks about the social world of squatting and C-Squat particularly, over the past 13 years. Williams discusses gender relations and allocation of space in the building, and talks about the legalization process and the changes and challenges that came with it. Williams, who studied archeology at Brooklyn College, describes her decisions that led her to seek an education, and later her decision to not continue pursuing an academic career. She began working IT and accounting at a publishing company, and she discusses how squatting and legalization shaped her choices in life. She also discusses how she learned construction skills and built her apartment.
    Erin Williams was born and raised in northern Vermont in 1979, and was the child of back to the landers. As a teenager she was into punk rock and at age 17 she left Vermont for Montreal. In 1999, after travelling for a few years, she settled in New York City and was voted into C-Squat after living there with a friend.
  - Fran Luck: Oral History Interview by Amy Starecheski, 2012-08-28; 564864; 1.62 Gigabytes in 4 files. (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_OH_68_ER_10)
    In this interview Fran Luck describes the Tompkins Square Riots of 1988 as the events that radicalized her and brought her into contact with the squatting scene. She discusses the contrast between the squatting movement and Cooper Square and the Village Independent Democrats, with which she had been involved previously. She describes the squatter's political analysis, emphasizing planned spatial deconcentration and framing gentrification as genocide and the growing connections between organized homeless people and squatters. Luck moved to the Lower East Side in the 1960s and describes the neighborhood as a bohemian enclave, and the process of gentrification starting in the 1970s. In this interview Luck also talks about the squats in the 1990s, focusing on how they were organized, their politics, and problems with bullying, domestic violence, and sexism. She focuses on the sexism in the political wing of the movement and the dynamics of anarchism and communism. Luck also talks about the feminist radio show she hosted on Steal This Radio, which later moved to WBAI. Finally she discusses evictions (8th Street, 13th Street, ABC Community Center, Doc Blocos) and the process of legalization.
    Fran Luck is a longtime housing activist and supporter of the squatting movement. She was raised in a lower-middle class Jewish family in New York City and came to the Lower East Side while she was a Cooper-Union student in the early 1960s. Luck worked in typography and became involved in the Second-wave feminist movement. She lived in a small apartment in the Lower East Side since the 1970s, and was not able to move because she could not find affordable housing elsewhere. Luck describes the neighborhood as a bohemian enclave, and the process of gentrification starting in the 1970s. In that environment of decentralized authority, she began organizing demonstrations, although she was viewed with suspicion as an older woman not involved in the squatting lifestyle. Luck organized the Lower East Side Squatting Support Committee to rally the support of respected organizations for squatters. She also describes the power squatters and their allies had in the aftermath of the Tompkins Square Riot. Luck was part of the second six-week occupation of ABC Community Center and describes her experience of that, particularly the misogyny of some occupiers and conflicts between communists and anarchists. After that occupation she started anti-gentrification organizing, founding RAGE ON - Revolt Against Gentrification Erasing Our Neighborhood.
  - Geoff Dann: Oral History Interview by Amy Starecheski, 2012-05-23; 564862; 428.5 Megabytes in 5 files. (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_OH_68_ER_12)
    In this interview Geoff Dann talks a lot about the difference between the neighborhood when he first moved into the Lower East Side and the neighborhood in 2012. He expresses nostalgia for how free and dangerous the neighborhood was in the late 1980s and early 1990s. He also talks about the decision-making process within Umbrella house, how people were given spaces in the squat, and how people were evicted from the building. Dann expresses his dislike for what he sees as the overly political attitudes and actions of his fellow squatters and of the legalization process.
    Geoff Dann was born and raised near Madison, Wisconsin. In July 1989 he moved to New York City where he immediately got an apartment in Umbrella House.
  - George Marco: Oral History Interview by Amy Starecheski, 2012-06-12; 564861; 472 Megabytes in 4 files. (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_OH_68_ER_13)
    In his interview, George Marco talks about his experience moving from one squat to another and then away from New York City. He also talks about his ideas about squatting, or homesteading as he prefers to call it, which are pro-legalization. He discusses his priorities in a building, which focus on getting the gas, heat, water and electricity turned on immediately. At 4th Street he and several other people quickly brought the building up to code, took legal action and became owners of the building, after which Marco sold his space in the building. Marco believes this should be the objective of all squatters but acknowledges that there are different objectives and different personalities within the movement.
    George Marco was born and raised in New York City, predominately in the Hell's Kitchen area. He first went down to hang out on the Lower East Side in the early 1980s and moved into a squat in 1986. When that squat started becoming overtaken by the drug crowd, Marco moved to Serenity House, which had just opened at the time. Next he spent a brief period of time in Bullet Space and then went back to Serenity and later helped open a squat on 10th Street. After 10th Street he opened and legalized a building on 4th Street, but then quickly sold his space in the building and left New York. Since then he has lived in various places in and out of New York. At the time of the interview he lived with his wife in Pennsylvania, but was planning to move back into the squat on 10th Street. He and his wife are performance artists who work with fire.
  - Howard Brandstein: Oral History Interview by Amy Starecheski, 2012-05-02; 564860; 642 Megabytes in 6 files. (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_OH_68_ER_14)
    Howard Brandstein's interview discusses his work with different organizations and the evolution of the homesteading and affordable housing movements in New York City. He discusses not-for-profit housing versus for-profit housing. He also comments on the some key differences between homesteading and squatting.
    Howard Brandstein was born in 1953 and grew up in Washington Heights, Manhattan. Brandstein attended Stonybrook University where he did his senior thesis on urban homesteading. In March of 1978 Brandstein began work with the Adopt-a-Building program and from there worked with a variety of other housing organizations.
  - Jen Kaminsky: Oral History Interview by Amy Starecheski, 2012-08-25; 564859; 9.16 Megabytes in 4 files. (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_OH_68_ER_15)
    This is the second interview Amy Starecheski conducted with Jen Kaminsky. The first covered Kaminsky's personal history and discussed how she ended up working at UHAB, as well as an overview of the squat legalization process, which was not recorded. This session was conducted via Skype video call, but only the audio has been recorded. This interview focuses on Kaminsky's observations of how squatters responded to and engaged with the legalization process. She discusses the appropriate role for non-profits like UHAB to play in a squatting campaign, assisting the squatters at their request. She discusses the romanticization of squatting by organizers in Buffalo where she worked most recently, in comparison to the real and difficult experience on the Lower East Side. She also talks about people's conflicted feelings about commodifying their housing and commercial spaces and the city's role, as the original legal owner of the buildings, in shaping the parameters of the legalization deal. She talks about warehousing and evictions in the legalizing squats. Kaminsky also discusses the challenges faced by the most marginal people during the legalization process, and the ways that people's responses to the process varied along class and gender lines, especially in terms of leadership. Additionally Kaminsky discusses the risk of foreclosure of HDFCs.
    Jenifer Kaminsky is an urban planner whose work focuses on community development and creation of affordable housing. At the time this interview was recorded, she resided in Buffalo, New York, where she served as Housing Director for the Buffalo Neighborhood Stabilization Co. (BNSC), the housing development arm of People United for Sustainable Housing (PUSH). In this capacity, she has led BNSC's efforts to create high quality, green affordable housing on Buffalo's West Side and reclaim vacant lots as opportunities for storm water management and community green space. From 2007-2011 she was Senior Project Manager at the Urban Homesteading Assistance Board (UHAB), where the Lower East Side squat legalization was one of her major projects.
  - Jessica Hall: Oral History Interview by Amy Starecheski, 2012-08-14; 564857; 344 Megabytes in 5 files. (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_OH_68_ER_17)
    Jessica Hall discusses the difficult process of getting a space in the building where she lived at 209 East 7th Street, everyday life in squats, and her run-in with Child Protective Services. As the secretary for the building she talks about decision-making processes and the shift over time from construction work to administrative work. She was deeply involved in the legalization process and talks about the negotiations with UHAB, and in particular the debates over debt and resale value. As a homemaker, Hall talks about the impact of that on her life choices and her decision to go back to school to become a social worker. Finally, she talks about what the gender dynamics and everyday life in the building have been like in recent years.
    Jessica Hall grew up in rural Maine. She moved to New York City to study theater at New York University, fell in love and started a family. In 1995 Hall was an activist and stay at home mom, living on Avenue A and struggling to pay the rent, when her family decided to move into a squatted building at 209 East 7th Street. A few years after her family moved into the squat, she became the building's secretary. She was also a homemaker and later went back to school to pursue a career as a social worker.
  - Anonymous: Oral History Interview by Amy Starecheski, 2012-08-11; 564856; 396.85 Megabytes in 5 files. (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_OH_68_ER_20)
    In this interview the interviewee discusses witnessing the legalization process from the perspective of a relative outsider (the interviewee was not a full member of the building until after the process was already underway). The interviewee talks about the unique way that they got access to their apartment and the back-and-forths that happened with the interviewee and other rooms and other buildings. This interview contains a lot of insight about the rules of squatting and how things changed with the legalization of the buildings.
    Conditions Governing Access
  - Lawrence Van Abbema: Oral History Interview by Amy Starecheski, 2012-04-04; 564855; 432.4 Megabytes in 4 files. (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_OH_68_ER_21)
    In his interview Lawrence talks about the reasons why people end up squatting. He recounts his role in fighting against the eviction of 13th Street and his involvement in the punk rock scene, which had a lot of influence on his work as an artist. He also discusses the legalization process and his reasons for favoring the legalization of his building.
    Lawrence Van Abemma was born in 1962 and raised in the Midwest. As a youth he moved around frequently, living and attending school in several different states. He moved to New York City from Minneapolis after dropping out of college to pursue a career as an artist. In 1989 he moved into a space in Umbrella House.
  - Marisa DeDominicis: Oral History Interview by Amy Starecheski, 2012-08-30; 564854; 618.35 Megabytes in 5 files. (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_OH_68_ER_23)
    Marissa DeDominicis describes her initial involvement with a group organizing to occupy vacant buildings, and their entry into 539 East 13th Street. She discusses her move to 544 East 13th Street following a fire at 539. In this interview she talks about her deteriorating relationship with the father, conflicts over the apartment, and the overall deterioration of social relations in the building. She describes her experiences as a single mom and the challenges of negotiating a custody battle as a squatter. DeDominicis describes the process of negotiating the legalization deal, and her disappointment that people wanted to sell for market rate, and her decision to leave 544.
    Marisa DeDominicis was born in 1962 in Beacon, New York. She grew up in a working class family. She moved to NYC in 1983 and became involved with community gardens and squats on the Lower East Side. She moved into a squat at 539 East 13th Street through her involvement with an activist group that was organizing to occupy vacant buildings. DeDominicis moved into a squat at 544 East 13th Street following a fire at 539. She had a baby in 544 in 1988, and continued to live in the building until 2003.
  - Marta Dann: Oral History Interview by Amy Starecheski, 2012-01-23; 2012-04-12; 564853; 1.54 Gigabytes in 7 files. (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_OH_68_ER_24)
    In this interview Marta Dann describes the intense community formed by squatters struggling to live in difficult circumstances together, and the challenges of dealing with issues of race, class and gender. She discusses the birth of her son, and her experience of raising a child in a squat. She also talks about how the building has changed over time, becoming more individualistic and rule-bound, especially with legalization.
    The digital access copy of this interview is available by appointment in the Special Collections Reading Room. Email special.collections@nyu.edu to make an appointment. It will be eligible for streaming in starting in 2020.
    Marta Dann was born in Portugal and came to the United States in the mid-1980s. She worked as a nanny in New Jersey and later moved to New York City. After nearly becoming homeless, she moved into Umbrella House in 1989, shortly after the building opened.
  - Nigel Clayton: Oral History Interview by Amy Starecheski, 2012-06-10; 2012-06-14; 564852; 727.3 Megabytes in 6 files. (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_OH_68_ER_25)
    During the first session of the interview Nigel Clayton talks about the shoddy construction UHAB did on his apartment and all of the trouble he had with UHAB and with the legalization process. During the second session Clayton discusses his connection to the Lower East Side and why he choose to be homeless there instead of find an apartment anywhere else in the city. He attributes his loyalty to the East Side to its singular vibe and to the music scene. He also talks about his experience as one of the few black people involved in the squatting scene and the difficulty of maintaining a space in an apartment if you were a minority. Nigel also shares his thoughts and feelings about the legalization process and specifically, how complicated and unfair he found the UHAB legalization process. Nigel ends the interview talking about his daily life and his routine and his objectives of getting a job in radio.
    Nigel Clayton was born in 1968 in Bridgeport, Connecticut. He originally came to New York City to work for Chrysalis Records in 1988. Nigel was homeless when he came to New York and bounced between staying in squatted buildings and living on the streets. Eventually, a friend invited him to share a room at Dos Blockos. Nigel lived at Dos Blockos from 1991 to 1998, when the entire building was evicted. After being homeless again for a short while, Nigel was offered a fully furnished space in Serenity House.
  - Osiris: Oral History Interview by Amy Starecheski, 2012-09-15; 564851; 571.26 Megabytes in 4 files. (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_OH_69_ER_26)
    In this interview Osiris (pseudonym) discusses his process of deciding to move into Umbrella House, knowing it was a squat and a space with no water, heat, or windows. He moved into Umbrella house sometime around 2000, thinking it was temporary, and a better option than imposing on friends. Osiris discusses his shift in thinking about his place when he found out about the legalization deal. He also talks about the process of getting and renovating his space. He talks about the stigma of living in a squat and the politics and morality of squatting. Osiris describes the meetings and governance of the building. He also describes the liberating experience of having affordable housing and talks about how the building chooses new members.
    Osiris (a pseudonym) is Chinese American, from the Bay Area. He attended University of California Berkeley, had a background in design, and renovated three rental apartments before he began squatting. He started living in Umbrella House in 2000.
  - Peter Spagnuolo: Oral History Interview by Amy Starecheski, 2011-03-27; 564850; 2.5 Gigabytes in 5 files. (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_OH_68_ER_27)
    Peter Spagnuolo describes the social and physical structures of the squats. He also discusses the heroin cultures in the Bay Area and New York City in the 1980s. Spagnulo was deeply involved in the adverse possession suit filed against the city in 1994-95, and talks about that process in detail. He also discusses his archiving practices in this interview.
    Peter Spagnuolo was born in 1965 and lived in seven different places before he was 18. He saw the Ramones in a strip mall in Long Island in 1979 and spent his high school years coming into the New York City to hang out, do acid in the Metropolitan Museum of Art, and explore the Lower East Side. While studying poetry at the University of California Berkeley he became addicted to heroin and moved into a squat. He moved back to New York, worked full time at the Strand Book Store, and in 1988 moved into a squat on East 13th Street after losing his apartment in Williamsburg.
  - Popeye: Oral History Interview by Amy Starecheski, 2012-04-17; 2012-06-03; 564849; 452.7 Megabytes in 5 files. (Box Electronic Records, E-records TW_OH_68_ER_28)